Bertie Routh Barron papers, Inclusive: 1897-1972, undated, Bulk: 1897-1900
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Bertie Routh Barron papers
Inclusive: 1897-1972, undated, Bulk: 1897-1900
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
245
Barron, Bertie Routh Webb, 1880 - 1914
2 document boxes.
The Bertie Routh Barron papers contains correspondence, financial documents, literary productions and photographic materials pertaining to the life of Bertie Routh Barron, particularly the time she spent at Baylor Female College.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Bertie Routh Barron was born in Plano, Texas, in 1880 to James M. and Virginia "Jennie" Barron. Her family was active at First Baptist Church Plano, so it is not surprising that she would attend a Baptist college. After graduating from Baylor Female College in 1900, Bertie went on to marry Alanzo Webb and the couple had one child, Robert B. Webb. Bertie Routh Barron passed away in 1916.
Scope and Content
The Bertie Routh Barron Papers include correspondence, financial statements regarding Bertie's expenses while at Baylor Female College, a history of the Jacob Routh Pioneer Cemetery as well as a history of First Baptist Church of Plano. This collection begins in 1897, when Bertie moves to Belton. The Correspondence series is by far the largest series of the collection. Also included are portraits of Bertie Barron and her parents, James M. and Virginia "Jennie" Barron.
Bertie Routh Barron attended Baylor Female College for three years in the 1890s. Baylor Female College would eventually become the University of Mary Hardin-Baylor. Barron wrote many letters to her family in Plano, Texas, during her time in Belton, and it is these letters that serve as a centerpiece for this collection. These papers are unique in that they provide an insight into women's higher education during the turn of the century.
During her time at Baylor Female College, Bertie wrote of many aspects of life in the female college. She recounts her experiences with professors, meals, grades, church, roommates, and traveling, allowing the reader a window into her world. Other documents and photographs included in these papers describe college grading, the costs of attending college, and relationships within the Barron family.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid, the Bertie Routh Barron papers were organized chronologically and according to type. A comprehensive inventory was available, and a finding aid had been written. This collection is arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, III. Literary Materials, and IV: Photographic Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 245. Acquired 1976-04-13
Related Resources
Related references
James, Eleanor. “University of Mary Hardin-Baylor.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 August 16.
Mabry, Meriworth McMillan. University of Mary Hardin-Baylor Sesquicentennial, 1845-1995. Belton, Tex:The University of Mary Hardin-Baylor, 1994.
Winfred A. Cheaney. Chapters From Life: A Tale of Our Baylor. Florence, MA: The Bryant Printing Company, 1898.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor Female College -- History.; Baylor University -- History.
Subjects
Education, Higher -- Texas -- History.; Universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- History.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1897-1900; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence from and about Bertie Routh Barron accounting for her time spent at Baylor Female College. Within the correspondence, Bertie relates stories of her academic pursuits, friendships and living conditions at the university. This series also includes correspondence from Baylor Female College to Bertie’s father, James M. Barron and various correspondence from Barron family members. This is the largest series in the Bertie Routh Barron Papers. It is in good condition.
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1897 September 12- September 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1897 October 2- October 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1897 October 31- November 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1987 December 5- December 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 January 11- January 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 January 30- February 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 February 20- March 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 March 20- April 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 April 10- May 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 September 10- September 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 September 25- October 9 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 October 16- October 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 November 6- November 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bertie Routh Barron to Family, 1898 November 27- December 19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Baylor Female College to James M. Barron, 1898-1900 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General, 1884 March 14- September 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General, 1885 February 24- March 15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Financial Documents, 1898-1900; 2
  General condition: Excellent.
  This series includes financial statements from Baylor Female College regarding Bertie’s schooling. Included are listings of all expenses she incurred. This series is in excellent condition.
  - School Records, 1898-1900 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Literary Productions, 1899-1972, undated; 3
  This series includes grade reports, newspaper clippings and two essays regarding Bertie Routh Barron’s matriculation at Baylor Female College. This series is in good condition.
  - Grade Reports, 1899-1900 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1930-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - History of First Baptist Church in Plano, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - “The Jacob Routh Pioneer Cemetery”, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Keith Krawczynski: ”Bertie Baylor: Student Life at Baylor Female College in the Late 1890s", 12/11/1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographic Materials, 1906, undated; 4
  This series includes portraits of Bertie Routh Barron and her parents, James M. and Virginia “Jennie” Barron. This series is in good condition.
  - Portraits, 1906, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)